Guide to the History of Medicine artifacts collection, 1550-1980s RL.10155
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Dr. Josiah Charles Trent Collection Artifacts, approximately 1650-late 19th century, over 50 items
  - R. & J. Beck Compound binocular microscope, mid-19th century (Artifact-box 165, Item htrent0001)
    Signed: R. & J. Beck, London & Philadelphia, 8292. Brass and lacquer microscope with curved "Lister Limb" (the arm which attached to the body tube to the base) which was designed by Joseph Jackson Lister.
    The firm began as Smith and Beck in 1847 and became R. & J. Beck in 1869 and eventually Beck & Beck. It was one of the first British makers to develop factory production methods and to manufacture to standard dimensions.
    Received from: Dr. Josiah Charles Trent
  - Compound monocular microscope, early 19th century (Artifact-box 37, Item htrent0002)
    Entirely of brass, including the round base. The wooden case has a few surviving accessories including: a small case of specimen slides with identifying label inside the top of the case. It is unsigned.
  - Culpepper-type compound monocular microscope, 18th century (Artifact-box 84, Item htrent0003)
    Unsigned. Brass with scrolled legs.
  - Compound monocular microscope, after 1875 (Artifact-box 185, Item htrent0004)
    This unsigned brass microscope is mounted on a rectangular metal base with a black matte finish. The stage is supported by two round pillars and can be adjusted to tilt. The body-tube swivels from the pillar to which the stage is attached and has a bull's-eye condenser fixed to the front on a jointed arm. The mirror is missing.
  - Bull's-eye condenser, undated (Artifact-box 48, Item htrent0005)
  - Pillischer achromatic microscope, approximately 1870 (Artifact-box 297, Item htrent0006, Artifact-box 212)
    Compound binocular, signed: M. Pillischer, London, No. 1441. This brass microscope has four high-quality objective lenses and two sets of eyepieces housed in the original wooden case with brass handle.
    A great advance in optics was achieved in the mid 19th century with the development of achromatic lenses. These employed a combination of lens elements, constructed from two or more different types of glass, to correct the spherical and chromatic aberations that had limited the image quality and resolution of lenses for the previous two hundred years. The optical binocular vision is different from that in modern microscopes. It reduces resolution slightly but gives a stereoscopic image.
  - Zeiss compound monocular microscope, 19th century (Artifact-box 166, Item htrent0007)
    Signed: Carl Zeiss, Jena, No. 27233. Brass with black lacquered iron base. Wooden case with metal label: E. Admet, Paris. Accessories include lens and occulars.
    Dr. Carl Zeiss founded a business in Jena, Germany and began making microscopes in 1847. His was the dominant optical firm in the world from the beginning of the 20th century through 1945 when it was separated into two firms following partition of Germany after World War II. Many firms have been associated with the Zeiss firm and have produced Zeiss products under license or as partners. Bausch & Lomb, which originated in Rochester, N.Y. in 1853, was among those.
  - Screw-barrel microscope, 18th century (Artifact-box 197, Item htrent0008)
    Simple monocular microscope, signed E. Culpepper, Londini. Brass with ivory handle. Housed in a small box covered in fish-skin and lined with green velvet. Some of the original parts are missing (notably the extension for opaque objects); however, it does include: six brass-mounted objectives, four ivory sliders, one brass slider, or animalcule cage, for living specimens, one opaque specimen holder with black and white disks and forceps, and one small ivory talc box.
    Developed by 1710, the brass screw-barrel microscope was the most common pocket microscope produced by instument makers in the 18th century. Intended primarily for tranparent specimens, this single lens microscope's small size, ease of use, and low price made it quite popular among amateurs. Normally held by an ivory handle screwed to the side of the body, the microscope could also be mounted via a ball joint at the top of a pillar which stood on a flat tripod. Over time many modifications were made to the original design and numerous accessories were employed which allowed a broader range of use.
  - Nkisi Nkondi, African healing statue (Artifact-box 41, Item htrent0009)
    Nkisi Nkondi. African healing statue. BaKongo, Congo - between 1880 and 1910. Wood, pigment, metal and glass.
    Minkisi (singular nkisi) are ritual objects used by the BaKongo (people of the Congo) for oath taking and healing. They are complex objects that derive their power from the dead, and to them, paradoxically, have been attributed the abilities both to afflict and to heal, to visit good as well as evil on a person.
  - Mortar and pestle (Artifact-box 271, Item htrent0010)
    Made of brass, with decorative abstract floral design on the outside of the mortar.
  - Mortar and pestle, 1869? (Artifact-box 270, Item htrent0011)
    Bronze, with two small decorative handles on the sides of the mortar. The outside of the mortar is ringed with fleurs-de-lis with a single unidentifiable medallion on the front. Signed: Nicolas Buret (?). On bottom of mortar: 1869 XVIII --- [remainer illegible]
  - Inro medicine box, undated (Artifact-box 133, Item htrent0012)
    Five-compartment box of carved brown laquer, unidentitied origin. Scene depicts a scholar sitting in a pavillion.
    Inro, first made around 1600 in the form they are known today, are small, highly decorated, multicompartmented boxes or cases that mainly carried medicines, tobacco, cosmetics, or perfumes.
  - Inro medicine box, undated (Artifact-box 132, Item htrent0013)
    Five-compartment box, painted red and gold on a black laquer ground and depicting a pastoral scene with bamboo fence and screen. Unidentified origin.
  - Home medicine chest, approximately 1830 (Artifact-box 205, Item htrent0014)
    English-made, in a walnut case in double-fronted cupboard style with ivory knobs and brass drawer pull. Accessories include scales, mortar and pestle, glass measuring cups and funnel. Custom made glass bottles with contents intact.
    Home medicine chests such as the walnut one shown here helped families to manage illnesses by having a convenient stock of ready made medicines close at hand. The typical chest contained an assortment of powders, tonics, and salves along with a copy of a home medical manual. An ivory crochet hook, found in a drawer of this chest, was used to hang the scales needed to weigh ingredients. Larger chests had additional bottles in a back compartment concealed by a sliding panel.
  - Ecorche, 18th century (Box 93, Item htrent0015)
    Italy; made of bronze.
  - Portrait bust of Dr. Josiah Charles Trent by Antonio Salemme (Artifact-box 141)
    Portrait bust of Dr. Josiah Charles Trent by Antonio Salemme. Bronze.
    Cast at Roman Bronze Works, Inc., Corona, NY. Dedicated on April 10, 1976.
    To view this item, please contact the Curator of the History of Medicine at the Rubenstein Library directly.
  - Carved ivory memento mori, approximately 1650 (Artifact-box 248, Item htrent0017)
    Carved ivory bas-relief skeleton, of unknown origin.
  - Scultetus bow saw, late 16th or 17th century (Artifact-box 46, Item htrent0018)
    Large amputating saw made of bronze and iron with hand-carved wooden handle, with tightening screw. 26.5" x 7.25". Meant for two-person operation.
  - Perrot-design bow saw, late 18th century (Artifact-box 187, Item htrent0019)
    Metal with wooden handle.
  - Trephination kit, 18th century (Artifact-box 85, Item htrent0020)
    Made of metal, with gull-wing handle; includes accessories in velvet-lined wooden case.
  - Horseshoe tourniquet, late 18th century (Artifact-box 83, Item htrent0021)
    Horseshoe tourniquet. Brescia [Italy], by Figini. Brass and leather.
    Signoroni's design executed by Figini.
  - Obstetrics forceps, undated (Artifact-box 216, Item htrent0023)
    Metal obstetric forceps.
  - Roman surgical instruments (Artifact-box 18, Item htrent0024)
    Roman surgical instruments. Replicas of bronze 3rd century CE instruments. 14 instruments.
  - Clothed female manikin on carved wooden couch, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 315, Item htrent0025)
    Couch is covered in red velvet. Made in France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, seperate organs. Hair and facial features are colored. There is also a fetus.
    Please contact the History of Medicine Collections Curator directly before coming to view this item.
  - Female manikin with ivory pillow on blue corduroy couch, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 179, Item htrent0026)
    Made in either France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs, and fetus.
  - Male/female pair with ivory pillow on wooden couches, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 309, Item htrent0027.1, Artifact-box 310, Item htrent0027.2)
    France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs. Includes fetus.
  - Female manikin with ivory pillow on wooden couch covered in striped brocade, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 346, Item htrent0028)
    Female manikin with ivory pillow on wooden couch covered in striped brocade. Couch has ivory feet. France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs. Includes fetus.
  - Female manikin with green silk pillow on couch with ivory feet, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 347, Item htrent0029)
    France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs, and fetus.
  - Female manikin with blue silk pillow on red silk couch with ivory feet, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 316, Item htrent0030)
    France, Germany or Italy. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs, with fetus.
  - Male and female manikin pair with ivory pillows on carved wooden couch with ivory ball feet, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 318, Item htrent0031.1, Artifact-box 319, Item htrent0031.2)
    France, Germany or Italy: 17th/18th century. Articulated, detachable plate, separate organs, and a fetus.
  - Female manikin with ivory pillow on wooden couch, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 311, Item htrent0032)
  - Female manikin with ivory pillow on wooden couch covered in green brocade, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 348, Item htrent0033)
  - Female manikin with ivory pillow in a red velvet-lined box with lid, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 317, Item htrent0034)
  - Female manikin with tilted head on brown velvet couch, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 180, Item htrent0035)
    France, Germany, or Italy. Not articulated, detachable plate, separate organs, and fetus.
  - Ivory box with bas-relief female anatomical manikin on cover, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 349, Item htrent0036)
    Made in France, Germany or Italy. Detachable plate, organs carved in place. Cover attached to box with metal hinge; the inside of the lid is painted
  - Ivory box with bas-relief female anatomical manikin on cover, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 312, Item htrent0037)
    France, Germany or Italy. Detachable plate, separate organs.
  - Male ivory standing manikin with head tilted to right, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 177, Item htrent0038)
    France, Germany or Italy. One of a pair of ivory figures. Not articulated, detachable plate, organs carved in place.
  - Female ivory standing manikin affixed to marble base, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 181, Item htrent0039)
  - Female ivory standing manikin with head tilted to left, 17th or 18th century (Artifact-box 178, Item htrent0040)
    France, Germany or Italy. One of a pair of figures. Not articulated, detachable plate, organs carved in place. Includes a fetus.
    Please contact the History of Medicine Collections Curator directly before coming to view this item..
  - Chinese diagnostic doll, 19th century? (Artifact-box 314, Item htrent0041)
    Ivory figure on carved base. Not articulated.
  - Chinese diagnostic doll, late 19th century (Artifact-box 313, Item htrent0042)
    Ivory figure with removable top-knot for possible use as a snuff bottle. Not articulated.
  - Chinese diagnostic doll, late 19th century (Artifact-box 182, Item htrent0043)
    Ivory figure on wooden couch. Not articulated.
  - Deathbed scene printer's block, undated (Box 105, Item htrent0044)
    On verso: In omnibus operibus moribund memorare novissima et in eternum non peccabit
  - Ivory memento mori double-faced figure, undated (Artifact-box 150, Item htrent0045)
    Young male/female pair and a skeleton.
  - Small ivory phrenological head, undated (Box 105, Item htrent0046)
    Made in England at an unknown date. Legend is in English.
  - Microscope (Artifact-box 183, Item HTRENT0047)
    Dr. Trent's microscope, given by Rebecca Trent Kirkland.
- Richard Vann Collection Artifacts, 19th century, 1 items
  Artifacts donated by Vann.
  - Wooden human anatomical model, 19th century (Artifact-box 47, Item hvann0001)
    Made in Germany; painted with various colors to show anatomical parts.
    Received from: Richard Vann, PhD.
- Warner Wells Collection Artifacts, approximately 1940s, 5 items
  Artifacts donated by Warner Wells, MD.
  - Hiroshima ceramic bowls and spoon, 20th century? (Box 26, Item hwells0001)
    Two white ceramic bowls, one short and one tall, each with a blue star below the inside rim. One small metal spoon.
    Picked up in the ruins of Hiroshima about 2 to 3 weeks after the bombing. The spoon, with the rice bowl, was treasured as a luxury item.
    Received from: Warner Wells, MD
  - Shishikarimon-nishiki: Guardian Gods Hunting Lion, 20th century (Box 26, Item hwells0002)
    Silk table runner. Kyoto, Osaka, Tokyo: Tatsumura Institute of Textile Art. Reproduction of Han Dynasty design. Housed in wooden box.
    One of the gifts given to Dr. Wells by Dr. Hachiya in appreciation for his help in translating "Hiroshima Diary."
- George D. Wilbanks Collection Artifacts, approximately 1750-1952, over 90 items
  Artifacts donated by George D. Wilbanks, MD and Evelyn R. Wilbanks, PhD.
  - Culpepper-type microscope, approximately 1750 (Artifact-box 149, Item hwilba0001)
    Signed: A. Abraham, Liverpool. Brass on wooden base with accessories. Elegant scrollwork legs. Original pyramidal carrying case.
    Received from: George D. Wilbanks, MD and Evelyn R. Wilbanks, PhD
  - Drum microscope, first half of 19th century (Artifact-box 351, Item hwilba0002)
    Compound monocular microscope, unsigned. Made of brass with cutaway on both sides.
    Popular in England between 1820 and 1850, the drum microscope evolved from a design introduced in 1738 by London optician Benjamin Martin, author of the "Pocket Reflecting Microscope." The name came from the drum-shaped section below the stage. Focusing was achieved by manipulating the telescopic body tube. This portable pocket microscope was typically made of thin brass with a round base and cut-out side. Some versions were sold in toy shops.
  - Drum microscope, first half of 19th century (Artifact-box 20, Item hwilba0003)
    Compound monocular, unsigned, made of brass with cutaway on one side. Housed in original wooden case with a few accessories still intact.
  - Apothecary boiler, 19th century (Artifact-box 365, Item hwilba0004)
    This lidded copper cooker was used to slowly simmer herbal preparations. The nickel cylinder held the fuel; the level of the flame was regulated by the knob on the brass base.
  - Invalid feeder, 19th century (Artifact-box 298, Item hwilba0005)
    White porcelain with red cross, handle and spout at 90 degrees.
  - Glass baby bottles, 19th century (Artifact-box 13, Item hwilba0006, Artifact-box 14, Artifact-box 15, Artifact-box 16, Artifact-box 194)
    Burr's patent nursing bottles. Blue-green glass. Patd Nov. 26th 1872.
  - Collection of syringes, 19th century (Box 92, Item hwilba0007, Artifact-box 65)
    1) Large pewter with wooden plunger (enema) 2) Small brass syringe with ivory nozzle (ear, vagina or mouth) 3) Medium stainless steel. Empire. Rutherford, NJ. Becton Dickinson & Co. (enema) 4) Medium stainless steel (enema) 5) Small stainless steel (ENT)
  - Medicine spoon, 19th century (Artifact-box 307, Item hwilba0008)
    England: Regnas. White porcelain with markings for table, dessert, or tea.
  - Covered medicine spoon with spout, undated (Artifact-box 306, Item hwilba0009)
    This dosing instrument is made of pewter.
  - Various cupping jars, 18th-19th centuries (Artifact-box 360, Item hwilba0010)
    Various cupping jars: 2 tin cupping jars, 9 blown glass, including one very large cup or 'Bonkus' with handle (Marbury, Patented: April 21, 1896)
  - Pocket leather case with medicine vials, late 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 336, Item hwilba0011)
  - Steel framed eyeglasses, late 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 200, Item hwilba0012)
    Housed in leather case stamped in gold: Hawkes Crystalized lenses. Extra lenses also present.
  - Pocket leather medicine case with six vials, 19th century (Artifact-box 254, Item hwilba0013)
    Louisville, KY: J.F. Kurfees [?] Co. Snap closure. Medicine vials are flat-ish.
  - Leather medicine case with ten vials, 19th century (Artifact-box 255, Item hwilba0014)
    New York: S.E. Massengill Company. Snap closure. Child's tablets.
  - Collection of 17 medical bottles, 19th-early 20th century (Artifact-box 296, Item hwilba0015)
    1) Schumann & Doescher - Prescription Druggists, New Orleans, Louisiana 2) Gombault's Caustic Balsam - Lawrence Williams Co. 3) Dr. Wistar's Balsam of Wild Cherry 4) Frey's Vermifuge - Baltimore 5) Davis' Painkiller 6) Dr. Robert Folger - Olosaionian, New York (blown) 7) Dr. D. Jayne's Alternative (blown) 8) Warner's Safe Kidney & Liver Cure (brown glass pressed, picture of a safe) 9) Balsam of Honey (card says "1950, dug in Lancaster, Pennsylvania") 10) Dr. Langley's Root & Herb Bitters - 99 Union Street, Boston (blown, green glass) 11) Ramon's Santonine Worm Syrup 12) Larkin smelling salts, Buffalo (green) 13) Unmarked except for "D" on bottom 14) Two clear bottles - one with fly dried in liquid 15) Clear glass bottle - unmarked (not an infant feeder)
  - Two apothecary jars, undated (Artifact-box 4, Item hwilba0016)
    Blown glass with glass labels: 1) Ac. Sulph D. 2) Ac. Nitric
  - Mahogany medicine chest with brass fittings, circa 1840 (Artifact-box 367, Item hwilba0017)
    Contents: glass stoppered bottles (some with labels), brass balance and weights, mortar and pestle, graduate, miscellaneous instruments. Includes a key.
  - Sterilizer, 19th century (Artifact-box 291, Item hwilba0018)
    Copper and brass.
  - Cabin-style doctor's bag with original contents, 1880s-1930s (Artifact-box 162, Item hwilba0019, Artifact-box 163)
    Brown leather bag with key. Handle is broken. Contents: medical instruments, hypodermic kits, needle and suture boxes, syringe cases in leather compacts.
    Used by Dr. Ellen E. Brown, Chester, Pennsylvania, in her practice. Given to the donor by Dr. John Longhead, Duke Ob/Gyn House Staff in 1960s.
  - Pap feeder, 1774 (Artifact-box 8, Item hwilba0020)
    London: William Justus. Silver with gilt interior. Engraved initials: JAO
  - Pap feeder, 1818 (Artifact-box 1, Item hwilba0021)
    London: Emes & Bernard. George III-era silver feeder in leather case with Hall & Co. Silversmiths, Manchester printed on lining of case.
  - Obstetrical instruments in canvas case, undated (Artifact-box 377, Item hwilba0022)
  - Baumanometer, wall board model, circa 1921 (Artifact-box 378, Item hwilba0023, Artifact-box 58)
    New York: W.A. Baum Co. Has two bags and cuffs.
  - Breast milk collector, circa 1918 (Artifact-box 191, Item hwilba0024)
    Pat. March 17, 1918. Glass.
  - Unidentified blown glass cylinder with base, undated (Artifact-box 356, Item hwilba0025)
  - Four glass nipple shields, undated (Artifact-box 192, Item hwilba0026, Artifact-box 193)
    Three are domed (each with a chip out of the rim), one is molded
  - Laboratory glass including blown glass retort, undated (Artifact-box 384, Item hwilba0027)
  - Various infant or invalid feeders, undated (Artifact-box 385, Item hwilba0028)
    Ten various feeders: classic gravy boat type (handle and spout in line); white with faint gold design, porcelain; blue "Delft" Royal Copenhagen type; flower, plain white porcelain - (11.L) marked on bottom; brown pottery "duck"; plain, porcelain white flowers; white porcelain "duck" Side spout (handle and spout at 90 degrees); painted china (large); plain white porcelain; white porcelain with red cross.
  - Large spatula with wooden handle, undated (Artifact-box 357, Item hwilba0029)
    Marked USA: Lampson & Gooduo Mfg. Co.
  - Small spatula with ebony handle, undated (Artifact-box 354, Item hwilba0030)
    Marked J. Rudell & Co., Green River Works.
  - Brass suppository mold, undated (Artifact-box 353, Item hwilba0031)
    Marked London: May Roberts. Screw-operated with 12 cavities.
  - Metal suppository mold, undated (Artifact-box 355, Item hwilba0032)
    Screw-operated with six cavities.
  - Pill roller, undated (Artifact-box 361, Item hwilba0033)
    Comes in two parts. Walnut and brass.
  - Octagonal ceramic pill tile, early 19th century (Artifact-box 80, Item hwilba0034)
  - Medical instruments, undated (Artifact-box 285, Item hwilba0036)
    Cervical dilator/catheter, small probe with wooden handle, metal syringe.
    Donated to Dr. Wilbanks by Dr. George Finola (Rush Medical College faculty).
  - Glass lantern slides for teaching obstetrics, late 19th to early 20th century (Artifact-box 217, Item hwilba0037)
    Philadelphia, PA: N.H. Edgerton. 33 wood-framed slides in wooden box.
  - Smellie-style obstetrical forceps with wooden handles, circa 1850s (Artifact-box 62, Item hwilba0038)
  - Smellie obstetric perforator, 19th century (Artifact-box 64, Item hwilba0039)
    Used for craniotomies.
  - Lenticular with pentagon end, 19th century (Artifact-box 2, Item hwilba0040)
    Ebony handle. Used in conjunction with trephine.
  - Trephine with ebony handle and one bit, 19th century (Artifact-box 277, Item hwilba0041)
  - Tooth key, undated (Artifact-box 278, Item hwilba0042)
    Ebony handle and one hook.
  - Small triangular leather medicine case, undated (Artifact-box 279, Item hwilba0043)
    Two tapered metal vials with rubber caps; one missing vial.
  - Long curved retractors with wooden handle, undated (Artifact-box 287, Item hwilba0044)
  - Folding uterine sound with bone handle, undated (Artifact-box 19, Item hwilba0045)
  - Telescopic ear trumpet with swivel bell, undated (Artifact-box 142, Item hwilba0046)
    Ear trumpet made of chrome.
  - Copper ear trumpet, undated (Artifact-box 257, Item hwilba0047)
  - Brass ear trumpet, undated (Artifact-box 137, Item hwilba0048)
    Once painted black. Dome-shaped.
  - Silver-plated Art Nouveau ear trumpet, approximately 1895 (Artifact-box 143, Item hwilba0049)
    Paris: Louis Lafont. Dome-shaped with decorative grill.
  - Spring lancet, 19th century (Artifact-box 31, Item hwilba0050)
    England: Wiegand & Snowden. Brass in leather case.
  - Folding lancets, undated (Artifact-box 61, Item hwilba0051)
    Tortoise shell handles. London: Evans. Plaid slipcase. Carried by Dr. Ella E. Brown of Chester, Pennsylvania in her doctor's bag.
  - Leather and wood medicine case with drawer, undated (Artifact-box 258, Item hwilba0052)
    Five bottles, three jars. Handle and clasp damaged.
  - Leather medicine case with bottles, undated (Artifact-box 259, Item hwilba0053)
    Six empty glass bottles with stoppers and metal screw caps. Case has two snaps.
  - Brass scales with weights, match holder, and prescriptions, undated (Artifact-box 260, Item hwilba0054)